Contact

(919) 607 - 2881 (Mobile) mthemphi@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ martinthemphill (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Leadership Microsoft Office Project Management

Languages

Chinese (Limited Working)
English (Native or Bilingual)

Certifications

Business Metrics for Data-Driven Companies

Martin Hemphill

Senior Financial Analyst at Advance Auto Parts Raleigh

Summary

Martin Hemphill is a Senior Financial Analyst working for TTI Floorcare NA in Operations Finance for Distribution and Transportation. Graduated from North Carolina State University with a BS in Business Administration with a Finance Concentration.

At TTI, Martin manages the financials for the full Distribution and Transportation network P&L. From month end reporting, variance analysis and research supporting the operations team.

While at North Carolina State University Martin was an early member initiated into the Fraternity of Phi Gamma Delta and was a part of the core team that grew the chapter from 8 members in 2010 to almost 50 members by end of 2014. Martin served two terms as the chapter Treasurer from 2011 to 2013 creating and implementing new processes into the chapters budgets and finances. Adapting and changing the financial system as the chapter grew in large numbers.

During the summer of 2014 from May to August Martin worked as an Intern at IBM in Production Procurement. While at IBM Martin performed in-depth analysis of product supply chains and Bill-of-Materials in order to find areas where improvements could be made. During this time Martin found an extreme interest in the areas of Data Science and proceeded to develop further in the Data Analytics field.

Martin started working full time at IBM upon graduation beginning January 2015 and worked on Process Mining and Data Mining projects for IBM Worldwide Production and Service Parts Procurement. Using new data analytics and tools Martin produced flow charts mapping processes to create actionable information from data. While further developing skill sets within Data Analytics Martin has continued through the field through data visualization, big data analysis, data mining and data compilation. Martin worked on an 6 person Agile team made up of various Engineers finalizing in the

submission of a patent application with regards to utilizing large data feeds and creating actionable information.

Experience

Advance Auto Parts
Senior Financial Analyst
December 2019 - Present (9 months)

Raleigh, North Carolina

TTI Floor Care North America
Senior Financial Analyst
July 2018 - August 2019 (1 year 2 months)

Charlotte, North Carolina Area

- Consolidation and month end reporting for Distribution and Transportation P&L
- Transformation of D&T month end reporting process with the introduction of new reports and insights allowing DC managers greater visibility towards labor spend, labor hours and overhead costs
- Transformation of compliance fine reporting and working with sales operations to drive significant reduction in customer fines resulting in 80% YOY reduction of customer penalties
- Value add investigative analysis into Distribution P&L to create a coherent actionable story for operations leaders
- Integration of Power Bi into reporting process to allow for real time dashboard analysis of D&T cost drivers and operational KPIs
- Created Cost to Serve model for all customers for sales team to achieve greater understanding of contribution by customer from D&T costs
- Leader in D&T operations working with all DC plant managers in understanding their P&L and cost drivers
- -Present findings and prepare variance driver explanations to Director and Operations leaders

Revlon

1 year 7 months

Senior Financial Analyst July 2017 - July 2018 (1 year 1 month) Oxford, NC

- Global leader for monthly consolidation of all factory variances and cost of goods produced

- -Work closely with six plant controllers worldwide assuring accuracy of financial data while providing reconciliation
- -Transformed monthly consolidation and reporting process to an all encompassing package that improves information and data integrity. New report introduced data visualization elements, improved integrity checks, simpler design allowing for standardization of reporting across all plants.
- Transformation of all processes and systems from Hyperion and Oracle to SAP and Management Reporting
- -Presentation to senior management for factory P&L including variance drivers and explanations each month

Financial Analyst

January 2017 - June 2017 (6 months)

Raleigh-Durham, North Carolina Area

- Responsible for monthly consolidation and analysis of Factory Variances and Cost of Goods Produced reports from each plant worldwide across all products. From report consolidation to value-add analysis of specific categories, line items, products, regions and markets.
- Maintain Monthly Gross Profit Bridge report for comparison of prior year to current along with YTD analysis. Report comprised of all plants involving all products, markets and categories.
- Work closely with business stakeholders to gather financial data and produce actionable information that addresses and highlights key business challenges.
- Maintain data repository of financial information while being able to perform ad-hoc analysis generating different perspectives, questions, answers and information from the data.
- Used Hyperion Financial Management and Oracle during month end close processes.

IBM

2 years

Supply Chain Analyst

January 2015 - December 2016 (2 years)

- -Conducting research on Process Mining theory and business applications towards IBM Service Parts Procurement, Storage brand and Power brand production
- -Proficient in Process Mining tools such as ProM and Disco

- -Create visual process maps from extracted real time event log data produced by SAP systems
- -Combine isolated data silos from different SAP instances to create singular data stream and format
- -Write and manage queries from QMF for workstation and Hyperion Intelligence Explorer on DB2 backbone
- -Deep dive analysis of processes to identify bottlenecks, loops and areas of efficiency using Process Mining and Data Mining analysis
- -Work in conjunction with IBM Watson Analytics to perform analysis on data sets from Production and SPP
- -Working in worldwide team settings using IBM Design Thinking and Agile development principles
- -Champion IBM Design Thinking and Agile Development practices using various tools such as TSC Resolution Rooms and Muraly
- -Attended multiple Design Thinking and Agile workshop hosted by IBM in Raleigh area becoming adept at Design Thinking and Agile methodologies

SSC 144 Coordinator (End Of Life Supply Chain Coordinator) January 2015 - December 2016 (2 years)

Raleigh-Durham, North Carolina Area

- -Conduct analysis on Field Replacement Units on Power Server (P Series) products withdrawn from market
- -Conduct analysis on Field Replacement Units on Appliance Brand products withdrawn from market
- -Compile candidate Field Replacement Units eligible for responsibility transfer from brand (P Series and Appliances) to Service Organization fulfilling IPRs and managing world wide inventory balance
- -Lead Agile project team through development via Agile methodology of new data feeds and tools responsible for monitoring supplier buffer in a visual on demand fashion
- -Using deep analytics tools and advanced Excel functions conducted quarterly scrap analysis for Z series brand
- -Worked with software development team to QA test and trouble shoot tools in development to automate manual processes within IBM Supply Assurance

IBM

Procurement Professional - Intern May 2014 - August 2014 (4 months)

research triangle park, nc

- Supply chain optimization for IBM Storage Products including DS8000 and $\ensuremath{\text{XiV}}$

- Create visual supply chain of various storage products to allow for efficient data sharing across different roles
- Bill of materials analysis, cost take-down analysis to find areas where cost saving opportunities can occur
- Pioneer department educational presentations featuring industry changes including Open Storage in Block, File, Object and Cloud Computing, IaaS, PaaS, SaaS

Phi Gamma Delta - Nu Sigma (NCSU) Chapter Chapter Treasurer November 2011 - November 2013 (2 years 1 month) Raleigh, NC

- Manage \$52,200 annual budget, increased revenue from \$24,000 to \$52,200 from 2011 to 2013
- Entered office in 2011 with \$20,000 debt owed, created new accounting system using excel and accounting principles to decrease debt to \$0 returning chapter to good standing
- Entered office in 2011 with only 30% collections rate on chapter accounts receivables, utilizing excel and accounting principles increased collections to 90% by 2013
- Created checks and balances system on own prerogative inform chapter of all financial decisions providing a high degree of transparency for current and future treasurers
- Managed four committees responsible for the performance of various chapter functions in fundraising, social events, philanthropy and special events
- Responsible for submitting monthly and annual financial reports, budgets and 501(c) tax documents to fraternity headquarters and IRS

City of Greensboro

4 months

Administrative Support Intern
June 2011 - August 2011 (3 months)

- Created physical and digital database of all parks and recreations volunteer information using Microsoft Access and Excel
- Integrated digital database to Parks and Recreations network infrastructure to allow for digital query, indexing and manipulation of information increasing efficiency of information flow
- Analyzed various proposals in response to cities RFP for a volunteer background checking system, created presentation highlighting different options and giving recommendations to department head

- Managed new and previous volunteers directing them to different requested community events balancing choice vs. needed manpower

Business Office Volunteer
May 2011 - June 2011 (2 months)

Business Office Greensboro Youth Council Family Carnival, prepare cash boxes, organized volunteers for ticket sales, tabbed cash boxes, team leader in running carnival business, manage project budgets, organize flow of cash.

Advanced Digital Broadcast Business Intern December 2009 - August 2010 (9 months) New Taipei City, Taiwan

- Prepare and analyze bill of materials using different vendors to calculate average costs for set-top boxes
- Attend operations meetings to learn how product lines are designed, developed, manufactured and shipped to customers
- Created new efficient signal center for set-top box prototype testing in order to reduce bottlenecks during testing phase of prototypes

Education

North Carolina State University - College of Management BS - Business Administration, Finance · (2010 - 2014)

Taipei American School

High School, High School/Secondary Diplomas and Certificates · (1996 - 2009)